<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of within the dioces of London, in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Richard Bishop of London, in his first generall visitation, holden in the fortieth yeere of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, Defender of the Faith,&amp;c.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1598</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1597-1604 : Bancroft)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847112</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847112</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00206)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of within the dioces of London, in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Richard Bishop of London, in his first generall visitation, holden in the fortieth yeere of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, Defender of the Faith,&amp;c.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1598</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1597-1604 : Bancroft)</author>
                  <author>Bancroft, Richard, 1544-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Valentine Simmes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES To be enquired of within the Dioces of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation of the Reuerend Father</hi> in God, Richard Biſhop of London, in his generall Viſitation,</p>
            <p>Holden <hi>In the fortieth yeere of the raigne of our moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> ſoueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON <hi>Printed by Valentine Simmes.</hi> 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb facs="tcp:12124:2"/>
            <head>¶ A Branch of the Statute made in the firſt yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Ladie Queene Elizabeth, intituled, An Act for the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformitie of Common prayer and ſeruice in the Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat from and after the feaſt of the Natiuitie of Saint Iohn Baptiſt next comming, all and euery perſon and perſons inhabiting within this Realme, or any other the Queenes maieſties dominions, ſhal diligently and faithfully (hauing no lawfull or reaſonable excuſe to be abſent) indeuour themſelues to reſort to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church or Chappell accuſtomed, or vpon reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable let therof to ſome vſuall place where common prayer and ſuch like ſeruice of God ſhall be vſed in ſuch time of let, vppon euery Sunday and other dayes, ordained and vſed to be kept as holidayes: and then and there to abide orderly and ſoberly during the time of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer, preaching or other ſeruice of God there to bee vſed and miniſtred, vpon paine of puniſhment by the Cenſures of the Church. And alſo vpon paine that euerye perſon ſo offending ſhall forfeit for euery ſuch offence twelue pence, to be leuied by the Churchwardens of the Pariſh where ſuch offence ſhalbe done, to the vſe of the poore of the ſame pariſh, of the goods, lands, and tenements of ſuch offender by way of diſtreſſe. And for due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution heereof, the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, the Lords tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and al the commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, doth in Gods name earneſtly require and charge all the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and other Ordinaries, that they ſhall indeuour themſelues to the vttermoſt of their knowledge, that the true and due execution heereof may be had through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Dioceſſe and Charges, as they will anſwer before God for ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills and plagues, wherewith almighty God may iuſtly puniſh his people for neglecting this good and wholeſome Lawe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:12124:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Tenour of the Othe miniſtred to the Churchwardens and Swornemen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall ſweare, that all affection, fauour, hatred, hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure, or malice ſet aſide, you ſhal vpon due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the articles giuen you in charge, preſent all and euery ſuch perſon of or within your pariſh, as hath committed any offence or fault, or made any default men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioned in theſe, or any of theſe Articles, or which are vehemently ſuſpected, or otherwiſe defamed of any ſuch offence, fault, or default: wherein you ſhall deale vprightly and according to trueth, neither of malice preſenting any contrary to trueth, nor of corrupt affection ſparing to preſent any, and ſo conceale the trueth, hauing in this action God before your eies, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine trueth, and to ſuppreſſe vice. So help you God and the contents of this Booke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charge">
            <head>¶ The charge of the Churchwardens and Swornemen, ſet downe for the better perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their dueties, and diſcharge of their Othes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey are ſtraitly charged to heare all theſe Articles read ouer to them, &amp; diligently to conſider and inquire therof. And for that the time is ſo ſhort in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation, that they ſhall not be able to make a perfect an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer vnto all of them, and that notwithstanding there are many noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious faults preſently worthy of preſentment and reformation, they are charged to make their anſwers vnto them preſently, ſo farre foorth as their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie ſhall now ſerue them. And to preſent now ſuch faults in their pariſh as at this time are worthie of preſentment or reformation, and that after their comming home betwixt this and Saint Martins day next they ſhall againe heare all the Articles read ouer vnto them, and diligently conſider and enquire thereof, requiring the Minister to aſſist them for the better performance of their duetie, to make a true and full an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in writing ſigned with their hands and markes, wherein they ſhall preſent aſwell all ſuch faults or offences contrary to the Articles as they forgot or omitted to preſent at the time of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation, as alſo all ſuch faults and offences contrarie to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles as ſhall happen and chaunce betwixt this and then.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:12124:3"/>
            <head>Articles to be enquired of within the Diocs <hi>of London in this viſitation holden in the yeare</hi> of our Lord God. 1598. Articles concerning the Clergie.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether is common prayer read by your miniſter in your Church or Chappell diſtinctly and reuerently vppon all Sundayes and holy daies, and in ſuch order as is ſet forth by the laws of this Realme in the booke of Common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, without any kind of alteration, omitting or adding any thing, and at due and conuenient houres.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether doth your miniſter vpon Wedneſdayes and Fridaies, not being holy daies, reade in your church or chappel, publikely the Letanie and other prayers appoynted in the ſayd booke for thoſe dayes, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he reade the comination againſt ſinners in ſuch order and forme as it is there alſo preſcribed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate in the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, or of baptiſme, when he ſolemnizeth matrimonie, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the dead, churcheth women &amp;c. vſe the formes and prayers preſcribed in the Communion booke, without omitting or altering any part of them, and without any of his owne additions.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether doth your parſon or Vicar reade publike prayer and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacraments ordinarily himſelf, vſing ſuch rites and ceremonies as are preſcribed in the booke of common prayer: as namely whether doth he knéele at the receiuing of the holy communion: make the ſigne of the Croſſe vpon the childes forehead in the adminiſtration of baptiſme: bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe any without Godfathers and Godmothers: vſe the ring in marriage: and generally whether doth he in the diſcharging of all theſe duties, and when he readeth common prayer, either vpon Sundaies holidaies, Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſdayes and Fridayes weare a ſurplice, or if you be ſerued with a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, whether doth he the ſayd curate obſerue all the ſayd particular rites and ceremonies mentioned in this article.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether doth your miniſter vppon Sundayes at morning prayer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto the pariſhioners what holyedaies and faſting dayes are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to be kept the weeke following: wherby they may be put in mind to prepare themſelues, and to repaire to the church to publike prayer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the lawes of the Realme.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether doth your parſon, vicar, or curate, or either of them reiect at
<pb facs="tcp:12124:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any time thoſe women being married which doo come to church to giue God thankes after their childbirth, or refuſe to viſit the ſicke, or to burie the dead, according to their duties preſcribed in the booke of common prayer.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether doth your miniſter in the Rogation dayes of proceſſion vſe the perambulation of the circuite of your pariſh, appoynted by her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Iniunctions: and whether doth he in the ſayd perambulation moue the people to giue thankes to God in the beholding of his benefits, for the increaſe and aboundance of his fruits vpon the face of the earth: and ſing or ſay the two Pſalmes beginning: <hi>Prayſe the Lord O my ſoule, &amp;c.</hi> with the Letany and ſuffrages therunto belonging: and at certaine conuenient places reade the homily of thankſgiuing to God, alreadie deuiſed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into foure parts, without addition of any ſuperſtitions ceremonie heretofore vſed.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether doth any man, being neither miniſter nor deacon reade com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer openly in your church or chappell, or adminiſter the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme, or ſolemnize matrimonie, or take vpon him to practiſe any other miniſteriall dutie in the church, that is preſcribed to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted particularly by ſuch as are either miniſters or Deacons: and what is his name that ſo doth.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether is your parſon or vicar apreacher, licenſed to preach by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authoritie according to her maieſties Iniunctions: if he be, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſermons doth he preach yeerely, if he be not, how many doth he procure to be preached by others: who hath preached them, and whether were they preachers licenſed, as is before expreſſed.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether doth your parſon, vicar or curate euerie ſunday when there is no ſermon, reade diſtinctly &amp; plainly ſome part of the Homilies preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and ſette forth by her maieſties authoritie.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Whether doth the parſon, vicar or farmour of the benefice in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh cauſe or ſuffer any curate or miniſter, either to reade ſeruice, &amp;c. or to preach, before he the ſaid curate being no preacher be examined &amp; admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ordinarie in writing: and before he the ſayde curate being a preacher be therevnto admitted according to her maieſties Iniunctions, and before they ſhewe theyr ſayde ſeuerall licences vnto the church-wardens.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether doth your Preacher in his prayer which he maketh at the entrance into his ſermon, vſe at al times the prayer for her maieſtie, with her whole title preſcribed in her highneſſe Iniunctions: as, Queene of England, France, and Ireland, defender of the fayth, &amp;c. and of all cauſes,
<pb facs="tcp:12124:4"/>
and ouer all perſons within her highneſſe dominions, as well eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall as temporall, next and immediatly vnder God, ſupreme gouernor: and whether doth hee in like manner then pray for the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, as by the ſayde Iniunctions it is alſo appoynted.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Whether your miniſter doth ſerue two cures in one day.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Whether doth your parſon, vicar or curate euery Sunday and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day openly in the Church earneſtly call for, heare, and inſtruct all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, apprentiſes, and ſeruants of both ſexes, that bee of conuenient age within your pariſh, or at the leaſt ſo many of them by courſe as the time will ſerue, and as he may well heare and inſtruct one houre at the leaſt, before or after euening prayer in the tenne commandements, the articles of the beleefe, and the Lords praier, and diligently examine and teach them the Catechiſme, as it is now allowed, and ſet forth in the booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether is there any man in your pariſh, being neither your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vicar, nor curate, that taketh vpon him to preach or reade lectures ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in priuate houſes, or publikely in your church or chappell, who is not licenſed ſo to preach or reade according to her maieſties Iniunctions, or who doth not once a yeare at the leaſt adminiſter the ſacraments in your ſaid church or chappell, where he ſo preacheth or readeth.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Whether your miniſter hath or doth receiue to the holy communion any perſons which he not of his owne pariſh, without teſtimonie from the miniſter of the place where they dwell, what they be, that it may appears that they be not perſons excommunicate or otherwiſe infamous.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Whether doth your parſon, vicar or curate adminiſter the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion vnto any communicants which do not receiue the ſame deuoutly and humbly knéeling vpon their knées, or whether doth he adminiſter it confuſedly to ſome knéeling, and to ſome, either ſitting or ſtanding, or wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p n="18">18 Whether hath your parſon, vicar, or curate, or other miniſter in your church or chappell, contrary to the order ſet downe in the communion book, and contrarie to her maieſties Iniunctions in that behalfe, admitted to the holy communion any open or notorious fornicator or adulterer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wicked liuer, by whom publike offence is giuen, without due penance inioyned by his Ordinarie firſt done, to the ſatiſfaction of the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and without ſuch further ſubmiſſion, as in the ſayd booke and Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is required.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Whether doth your parſon, vicar or curate, or any other miniſter or preacher, baptiſe in your pariſh church or chappel, any Infants, not in the
<pb facs="tcp:12124:4"/>
Fonte according to the ancient cuſtome, but in a baſon, and vrge the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of the ſaide infant to be preſent, and in place of Godfathers for their children.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Whether doth your parſon vicar, or curate once euerie quarter of the yeare reade her maieſties Iniunctions openly and deliberately before his pariſhioners at one time or at two ſeueral times in one day, according as in the ſayd Iniunctions it is preſcribed.</p>
            <p n="21">21 Whether hath your parſon vicar, or curate, or any other miniſter preached, declared, or ſpoken any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your pariſh in derogation of the booke of common prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is ſet forth by the lawes of this Realme, diſpraiſing, or deprauing the ſame, or any thing therein contained, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the preſent eſtate of the eccleſiaſticall gouernment, eſtabliſhed by the ſame authoritie, or againſt any office, function, or part thereof, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſame to be vnlawfull.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Whether hath your parſon or vicar more benefices then one, if hée hath not, whether is he reſident vpon that one: if he be not reſident, where doth he remaine, and by what authoritie is he abſent, and whether doth he leaue a ſufficient miniſter and preacher to ſupply his abſence, allowing ſomething yearely towards the releefe of the poore: and what doth hee ſo allow.</p>
            <p n="23">23 Whether is your perſon or vicar who hath two benefices within this Dioces: or one benefice in this Dioces, and another forth of the ſame, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent one half of the yeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one of them, and the other half yeare or the greater part thereof vpon his other benefice, and whether doth he leaue the benefice in your pariſh prouided of a ſufficient preacher to ſerue it: and hath an eſpeciall care of ſome conuenient hoſpitallity to be kept in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence according to his abilitie, and the proportion of that liuing.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Whether doth your parſon, vicar, or curate keepe a iuſt and perfect note of al ſuch as do communicate in your pariſh, and do not rather, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their priuate gaine, receiue their offerings at Eaſter, deliuer them tokens enter them into their booke, and ſo certefie as communicants thoſe who neuer receiued.</p>
            <p n="25">25 Whether doth your parſon, vicar, or curate keepe any man or woman in their houſes, that are ſuſpected to be, either of euil religion, or of badde life, or whether be they or any of them incontinent perſons themſelues, or giuen to drunkenneſſe or idleneſſe, or be haunters of Tauerns, alehou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or ſuſpected places, hunters, hawkers, dicers, carders, common table-players, ſwearers, dauncers, or otherwiſe ſuſpected perſons of any noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious crime, or light and vnſeemely behauiour, or giue euill example of
<pb facs="tcp:12124:5"/>
life, or vſe diſordered or vnſeemely apparrell, either in colours, guardes or light faſhion.</p>
            <p n="27">27 VVhether there be any miniſters or prieſts within your pariſh, which liue idlely without any cure, neither ſeruing in any place, nor hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place of reading or preaching, and ſo become offenſiue to their calling.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles concerning the Church.</head>
            <p n="1">1 VVhether haue you in your pariſh Churches and Chappels all things neceſſarie and requiſite for common prayer and adminiſtration of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, eſpecially the booke of common prayer with the new Kalender, two Pſalters, the Engliſh Bible in the largeſt volume of the edition ſette forth by the Biſhops, and lately imprinted by the Quénes Printer, the Table of the ten commandements, a conuenient pulpit well placed, a comely and decent Table ſtanding vppon a frame, for the holy Cmmuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with a faire linnen cloth to lay vppon the ſame, and ſome couering of ſilke, buckram, or other ſuch like for the cleane keeping therof, a faire and comely communion cup of ſiluer, and a couer of ſiluer for the ſame, which may ſerue alſo for the miniſtration of the communion bread, a decent large ſurples with ſléeues, and a ſtrong cheſt or boxe for the almes of the poore, with thrée locks and keyes to the ſame, and all other things neceſſarie in and to the premiſſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 VVhether there haue growne in your Church ſince the laſt viſitation in the yeare 1595. any contention betwixt any of the pariſhioners, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the placing or diſplacing of any in any ſeate or pew in the church, and whether there haue beene any pew builded ſince the foreſayd yeare 1595. in any your churches, without the expreſſe leaue and conſent firſt had of the Ordinarie of the Dioces, and by whom haue any ſuch been built.</p>
            <p n="3">3 VVhether is your Church or Chappell, and the Chauncell well and ſufficiently repaired and kept without abuſe of any thing: whether doth your Parſon, vicar, or curate, or the proprietarie or farmour of your parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage or vicarage in your pariſh keep the parſonage or vicarage houſe with al other the edefices therunto appertaining in good &amp; ſufficient reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and whether is your churchyard well fenced and cleanely kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any layſtall or other annoyances.</p>
            <p n="4">4 VVhether the Church of your pariſh be now vacant or deſtitute of an Incumbent or no, and if it be, how long it hath beene ſo, and who is the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, &amp; whether during the vacancie of the benefice, he occupieth the globe
<pb facs="tcp:12124:5"/>
land, and taketh the tithes and other fruites to him ſelfe during the time of vacation, or who elſe occupieth &amp; taketh the ſame, and by what authoritie.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether your church be a parſonage or a vicarage preſentatiue or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue, or otherwiſe ſerued by a curate: whether did they euer heeretofore heare or know that it was a parſonage or vicarage, and how came it to bee decayed from beeing preſentatiue, to be in the ſtate it nowe is, and when was it firſt decayed from being a benefice preſentatiue, as you remember.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether your fonts or baptiſteries be remooued from the place where they were wont to ſtand: or whether any perſons, leauing the vſe of them, do chriſten or baptize in baſons, or other veſſelles, not accuſtomably vſed in the church before time, or do vſe any kind of lauor with a remouable baſon, or haue taken downe the old &amp; vſuall font heretofore vſed in your pariſh.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether is there in your pariſh a ſufficient Regiſter booke of parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of marriages, chriſtnings, and burialls, prouided at the charge of the pariſh: whether are all the names of thoſe that haue bin, either chriſtned, maried, or buried ſince the beginning of hir Maieſties raigne newly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into the ſaide parchment booke: whether doth the Miniſter euery ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day reade the names publikely of thoſe, that were eyther chriſtned marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or buried the weeke before: whether haue you a publike cheſt with 3. lockes for the miniſter, and the two churchwardens to kéepe the ſaid booke in: and whether haue you brought a tranſcript of all the names of ſuch as haue been chriſtned, married, and buried this laſt yere into M. Blackwel my Regiſter his office, as you are bound to do euery yere hereafter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a month after the feaſt of Eaſter by the conſtitutions laſt authorized by her Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles concerning Eccleſiaſticall Officers.</head>
            <p n="1">1 Whether the Chancelor Archdeacon, Commiſſarie Official, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction in this dioceſſe, their Regiſters or Actuaries, Apparators, or Summoners, haue at any time winked at and ſuffered any adulterers, fornicators, inceſtes, or other faultes or offences preſented vnto them, to paſſe and remaine vnpuniſhed, and vncorrected for mony, rewards, bribes, pleaſure, frindſhip, or any other partial reſpect.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether doth the Chancellor, Commiſſaries, Archdeacons or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officialles heare any matters of office, or correction priuately in their chambers without the preſence of the ſworne Regiſter or his deputy, or do diſcharge any mans penance for mony, without the conſent of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, according to the laſt conſtitutions by her Maieſtie confirmed, or doe ſend any writing vnder their owne hands to your church, without the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters
<pb facs="tcp:12124:6"/>
preſence at the dooing of it, either for marriage of any couples, or for ending or ordering of any matter of office, correction, or penance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles concerning Schoolemaſters.</head>
            <p n="1">1 Whether the Schoolemaſter or ſchoolemaſters within your pariſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly or priuately in any noble or gentlemans houſe, or in any other place be of good and ſincere religion, life, and conuerſation, and be diligent in teaching and bringing vp of youth, and whether they haue béene exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, allowed, and licenſed for ſchoolemaſters by the Ordinarie or his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether your Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaſters do themſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy communion as often as they ought to doo, and whether they bring with them ſo many of their ſchollers as bee of age ſufficient, and of capacity by inſtruction to receiue the Lords ſupper, or els be able to giue teſtimonie in what church their ſchollers do receiue and heare pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayer.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether your Schoolemaiſter or Schoolemaiſters do orderly on ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes with their ſchollers come to the church of their pariſh where they teach, and there ſée their ſchollers placed in ſome conuenient place, ſo as they do not diſquiet the miniſter or pariſh in time of diuine ſeruice, but may exerciſe themſelues godly in reading and hearing the ſeruice and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and in anſwering with the congregation in reading of publike prayer.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether the ſchoolemaiſter or ſchoolemaiſters either priuate or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like do teach their ſchollers the Catechiſme authorized by publike autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, at the leaſt once euerie wéeke, and do inſtruct and examine them in the ſame, or do teach any other catechiſme, and what catechiſme it is that they ſo do teach.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether your ſchoolemaiſter or ſchoolemaiſters or any of them bee known or ſuſpected to reade vnto their ſchollers priuately any vnlawful books, or priuately to inſtruct them in their yong yeares either in pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſuperſtition, or diſobedience, or contempt to hir Maieſtie and hir lawes eccleſiaſticall by publike authoritie allowed.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether your ſchoolemaiſter or ſchoolemaiſters or any of them vnder preſence of Catechiſing their ſchollers, which is a moſt godly order, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully by them to be obſerued, do keepe lectures, readings, or expoſition in diuinitie in their houſes, hauing continuall repaire vnto them of people not being of their owne family and houſhold.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether the ſchoolemaiſter or ſchoolemaiſters within your pariſh do
<pb facs="tcp:12124:6"/>
teach his or their ſchollers any other grammer then that which is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the kings grammer, ſette forth by the authoritie of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles concerning pariſhioners and others of the Laitie.</head>
            <p n="1">1 VVhether all houſholders in your pariſh cauſe their children, ſeruants and apprentiſes, both mankind and womankind being aboue ſeuen yeares of age, and vnder twentie, which haue not learned the catechiſme, to come to the church on ſundaies and holidayes at the times appointed for cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, and there diligently and obediently to heare, and what bee the names of thoſe that do not cauſe their children, ſeruants, and apprentiſes ſo to come to the church to be inſtructed and examined.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether the church wardens do quarterly deliuer to the Archdeacon a note of al thoſe who do not ſend their children &amp; ſeruants to be catechiſed</p>
            <p n="3">3 VVhether any do worke or keepe any ſhoppe open vpon Saboth daies, or vpon any holidaies appointed by the lawes of this realme to be kept ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liday, or vſe any worke or labor, or open ſhew of their wares in any of thoſe daies.</p>
            <p n="4">4 VVhether you your ſelues or the Churchwardens in the yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you haue ſuffered any vnmarried women being begotten with child, to go out of your pariſh before ſhe hath done penance, or any man defamed of whoredome to depart vnpuniſhed, vppon direction appoynted by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie. And forth of whoſe houſes haue they gone away with child vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and how many vnmarried women which haue béene deliuered within your pariſh theſe thrée years laſt paſt, haue gone away without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of penance.</p>
            <p n="5">5 VVhether the pariſh Clarke be appoynted according to the law, by the parſon or vicar of the pariſh, with the allowance of the Ordinarie, and whether he be not obedient to the parſon, vicar, or curate, and whether hée be able to reade, and whether hée kéepe the bookes and ornaments of the Church faire and cleane, and cauſe the church, and quire, the communion table and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to bee kept cleane and decent againſt the ſeruice time, the communion, ſermon, and baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether there bee any perſon or perſons eccleſiaſticall or temporall within your pariſh or elſewhere within this Dioces, that haue retained and kept in their cuſtodie, or that reade, ſel, vtter, diſperſe, carrie, or deliuer to others any Engliſh bookes or libels, ſette forth either on this ſide or beyond the ſeas, by papiſts or others againſt the Quéens ſupremacie in cauſes eccleſiaſticall, or againſt true religion and catholike doctrine, or
<pb facs="tcp:12124:7"/>
the gouernment or diſcipline of the church of England, now within this realme reuiued and eſtabliſhed by common authority, and what theyr names and ſurnames are.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether there be any in your pariſh who are noted, knowne, or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to conceale or kéepe hidden in their houſes any maſſe bookes porteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, breuiaries, or other bookes of poperie &amp; ſuperſtition or any Chalices, copes, veſtments albs, or other ornaments of ſuperſtition, vncancelled or vndefaced, which it is to be coniectured they do kéep for a day, as they cal it.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether there be in your pariſh any popiſh or ſectarie recuſant or recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, which for any cauſe whatſoeuer forbeare or diſſwade and dehort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to come to Church to common prayer or to heare Gods word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, pretending it vnlawfull to come to our aſſemblies, as the church of England now ſtandeth, eſtabliſhed by her maieſties authoritie, and what their ſeuerall name or names are, and how long they haue béene recuſants.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether any do refuſe to receiue the holy communion at their owne miniſters hands, either becauſe he is not a preacher, or becauſe he duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the order of miniſtration appoynted by the booke, and who they be that do go from their owne pariſh, to receiue at any other miniſters hands.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether any of your pariſhioners hauing a preacher to their parſon, vicar, or curate, do abſent themſelues from his ſermons, and reſort to any other place to heare other preachers.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Whether all the people of your pariſh aboue 16. yeares of age, and eſpecially houſholders, hauing no lawfull excuſe to be abſent, doo reſort with their ſeruants and children to their pariſh Church or Chappel on the holy daies, and on the Sundayes to morning and euening prayer, and who they be that either negligently or wilfully abſent themſelues, or come ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late to the church vpon the Sundayes or holidaies, or that walke, talke, or otherwiſe vnreuerently behaue themſelues in the church, or vſe anie gaming or paſtime abroade or in any houſe, or ſitte in the ſtreete or churchyard, or in any tauerne or alehouſe vpon the Sunday or holiday in the time of common prayer, ſermon, or reading of the homilies, or any of them either before or after noone.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether the forfeiture of xii. pence for euerie time of abſence from the church vpon euerie ſunday and holiday appoynted by a ſtatute made in the firſt yeare of the Queenes maieſties raigne to bee leuied and taken according to the ſame ſtatute (the tenor whereof is ſette downe in the beginning of this booke) by the churchwardens of euerie perſon that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth, and by them be put to the vſe of the poore of the pariſh, if it bee
<pb facs="tcp:12124:7"/>
not ſo leuied, by whoſe fault it is?</p>
            <p n="13">13 VVhether there be in your pariſh who doo receiue into their houſes, keepe, harbour, or releeue, or which do reſort to any popiſh prieſt, or which be noted or ſuſpected to be ſeducers, and perſwaders of others by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample or doctrine to poperie or ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therby to alienate the Quéenes ſubiects from their due obedience and chriſtian religion, now by law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in England.</p>
            <p n="14">14 VVhether there be any Inkéepers, alewiues, victuallers, or tiplers, that ſuffer or do admitte any perſon or perſons in their houſes, to eate, drinke, or play at dice, cards, tables, bowles, or ſuch like games, in the time of common prayer or ſermon on the ſundayes or holidayes, or any Butchers or other that commonly vſe to ſell meate or other things in the time of Common prayer, preaching, or reading of homilies: and whether in any faires or common markets falling vpon the Sundayes, there be ſhewing of any wares before morning prayer be done: and whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny markets &amp; ſelling of wares be vſed or ſuffered in any churchyards on the Sabboth day by common packmen or pedlers going about, or anie Butchers.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether the Churchwardens of the laſt yeare haue giuen to the pariſh a iuſt account of the church goods and rents that were committed to their charge, according to the cuſtome that hath béene aforetime vſed: and what church goods they or any other haue ſold, and to whom, and whether to the profite of your church or no: and what hath bin done with the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereof comming?</p>
            <p n="16">16 Whether the churchwardens and ſworne men, ſince the fourth day of Auguſt, 1597. haue of any priuate corrupt affection concealed any crime or other diſorder in their time done in your pariſh, and haue not preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame to the Biſhop, Chauncelor, Archdeacon, Commiſſarie, or ſuch other as had authoritie to reforme the ſame: and whether they or any of them at any ſuch time as they ſhould haue béene at diuine ſeruice on ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes and holidaies, and ſhould there haue obſerued others that were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, haue béene away themſelues at home, or in ſome tauerne or alehouſe, or elſe about ſome worldly buſineſſe, or at bowles, cards, tables, dice, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gaming, without regarde of their office, and dutie in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Whether your miniſter and you the churchwardens, or any other in your pariſh haue in your reueſtries made any orders, or do vſe to call anie parties before you for any cauſe to be ordered by the eccleſiaſtical lawes, and ſo do vſe a kind of Preſbiterie or cenſuring ouer your neighbours, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of your veſtrie méetings.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <pb facs="tcp:12124:8"/>18 Whether any of your pariſh being of conuenient age, haue not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy communion thrice this laſt yeere at the leaſt, and namely, at Eaſter laſt or thereabouts for once, and what their names are, or which at their receiuing haue not ſignified the ſame before to your parſon, vicar, or curate, that he might conueniently examine them, and who haue refuſed to come to him to be examined.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Whether there be any in your pariſh that doth adminiſter the goods of thoſe that be dead without lawfull authoritie, or any that ſuppreſſe the laſt wil of the dead, or any Executors that haue not fulfilled their teſtators laſt will, eſpecially in paying of legacies giuen to the church, or to other good and godly vſes, as to the reléefe of pouertie, to orphants, poore ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, poore maidens marriages, hiewayes, ſchollers, and ſuch like, and by whom are they ſo deteined. And whether any ſuch legacies or goodes, of what kinde ſoeuer payde or deliuered to any godly or publique vſes ſince the beginning of her Maieſties raigne, be otherwiſe imployed, and not in ſuch ſort, and to that end for the which they were giuen.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Whether there be any in your pariſh, that ſince the fourth of Auguſt 1597. hath or doth offend contrary to the ſtatute made in the ſeauen and thirtieth yeere of the raigne of King Henrie the eight, for the reformation of vſurie, and reuiued by an Act made in the thirtéenth yeere of the raigne of the Quéenes Maieſtie that now is, taking aboue the rate of ten pounds for the lending of an hundred pounds by the yeere, and what be the names of ſuch offendors.</p>
            <p n="21">21 Whether hath your miniſter or any of the pariſh, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or priuitie of the Ordinarie, cauſed any to do penance, or be puniſhed either openly or otherwiſe for any crime puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes onely, and what be the names of the parties that haue beene ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and in what manner.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Whether the Iniunctions ſent from my Lords grace of Canterburie and the high Commiſſioners in Nouember 1587. directed to your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and churchwardens, not to receiue ſtrange Preachers not licenſed be obſerued, and whether the ſaide Iniunction remaine in your Church or no.</p>
            <p n="23">23 whether there be any amongſt you that do vſe ſorcerie or witchcraft puniſhable by the eccleſiaſticall lawes, or that be ſuſpected of the ſame: and whether any vſe any charmes or vnlawfull prayers: and whether any do reſort to any ſuch for help and councell, and what bee the names, both of ſuch as vſe it, and of ſuch as reſort to them for helpe.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Whether any couples that be married in priuate houſes within theſe
<pb facs="tcp:12124:8"/>
thrée yeares laſt paſt haue bin knowne or ſuſpected to haue bin married by any popiſh prieſt or otherwiſe, after any other order then is appoynted by the church of England.</p>
            <p n="25">25 whether there be among you any blaſphemers of the name of God, great or often ſwearers, adulterers, fornicators, harlots or whoremaſters inceſtuous perſons, bawdes, or receiuers of naughtie and incontinent perſons, or harborers of women with child which be vnmaried, conueying or ſuffering them to go awaie before they doe anie penance, or make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the congregation, or any that be vehemently ſuſpected of anie ſuch faults, or that be not of good name and fame touching ſuch crimes and faults of drunkards, or ribawds, or any that be malitious, contentious, or vncharitable perſons, railers, ſcolders, or ſowers of diſcord betwéen neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and eſpecially railers againſt miniſters, and againſt their marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</p>
            <p n="26">26 whether there be any in theſe partes that haue béene married within the degrées of affinitie or conſanguinitie, by the lawes of God forbidden, or anie that being diuorced or ſeparated for the ſame, do yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cohabite and kéepe company ſtil together, or anie that being married without thoſe degrées haue vnlawfully forſaken their wiues or huſbands, and married others, anie man that hath two wiues, or anie woman that hath 2. huſbands, any that being diuorced or ſeparated aſunder, haue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried again, anie that haue married and contracted themſelues without the conſent of their parents, tutors, or gouernors, any that haue maried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out banes thrice ſolemnely aſked, any couples married that liue not toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but ſlaunderouſly liue apart.</p>
            <p n="27">27 VVhether there be any in your pariſh who wil come to heare the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but will not come to the publique prayer appoynted by the Booke of common prayer, making a ſchiſme or diuiſion, as it were, betwéene the vſe of publike prayer and preaching. And whether there be any, who being preſent at publique praier, do not deuoutly and humbly knéele vpon their knées, at ſuch times as by the Booke of common prayer they are appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: to wit, when they make a generall confeſſion of their ſinnes: when all prayers and Collects are read: in the time of the Letanie: when the tenne Commaundementes are read, &amp;c. And what are theyr names that haue at any time ſhewed themſelues vnduetifull and vnreuerent in this behalfe.</p>
            <p n="28">28 Whether the miniſter and churchwardens haue ſuffered anie lord of miſ-rule, or ſummer lord or ladies, or any diſguiſed perſons, any players, or maie-games, or any moris dauncers, at any time to come vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:12124:9"/>
into the church or churchyard, and there to daunce or play, or ſhew them ſelues diſguiſed in the time of common praier, and what they be that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch diſorder, or that accompanied or maintained them, or any playes to be played in the church.</p>
            <p n="29">29 Whether there be any married women or others within your pariſh, which after childbirth refuſe or contemne to come to the church to giue God thanks for their deliuery, and to haue the praiers publikely appointed in that behalfe by the booke of common prayer.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Whether anie within your pariſh do reſort vnto barns, fields, woods, priuate houſes, or to any extraordinary expoſitions of ſcriptures, or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences together, and doe (as it were) make a ſeuerall church or ſect vnto themſelues, and be drawers or perſwaders of others to any ſuch ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or damnable ſects, and in whoſe houſes, or what places haue you heard of any ſuch méeting.</p>
            <p n="31">31 Whether any do kéepe their children vnbaptized longer than is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, vnles it be for ſickenes of the child, or other vrgent occaſion: And whether anie doe carrie their children from the pariſh they are borne in, to other pariſhes to be baptized, and ſo refuſe their owne pariſh, or doe bring ſtrange miniſters into their owne houſes to baptize their children priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to their owne fantaſies.</p>
            <p n="32">32 Whether anie notorious recuſant who obſtinately refuſeth to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker with the church of England in publique prayer, and hearing of the word of God preached, who is for his diſobedience and contempt excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, and ſo dieth excommunicate, be buried in chriſtian burial, not hauing before his death ſought to be abſolued, and teſtified the ſame his ſubmiſſion to ſome honeſt and diſcréete man, who ſhal vpon his othe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to the Biſhop of the Dioces, whereby his Lordſhip may giue order to the Ordinarie, before whom he was excommunicate for his abſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond billes, and in them the names are to be ſet downe of all ſuch as haue beene buried at any time ſince the ſeuenth day of Auguſt 1598, and likewiſe of ſuch as haue bin married by any licenſe, with the names of thoſe who graunted the licenſe euer ſince the ſaide ſeuenth of Auguſt, they are to be brought into Maiſter Blackwells office in Iuie lane, being the principall Regiſter to the Lord Biſhop of London betwixt the 26. of Nouember next, and the 4. of December then following, if there be not any other place appointed at his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſitting in Viſitation to bring them vnto.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12124:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
